# Cameron H. Matthews

1046 Via Vera Cruz San Marcos, CA 92078

(confidential)

Phone: (619)384-8520 9a-9p PT

cameronhmatthews@yahoo.com

### **Summary**

Technology executive with strong leadership ability, successful management skills, and proven organizational capabilities who possesses over 30 years of cross-vertical security, software, and systems engineering experience. Security and technology pioneer in the areas of threat intelligence exchange, rapid vulnerability notification, and security situational awareness. Areas of expertise include:

- Corporate security strategy
- Risk and threat management
- Corporate security culture
- Secure software and systems engineering
- Systems integration

## **Professional Experience**

Sentek Global San Diego, CA Dec 2006 – Oct 2018
Chief Security Officer
Chief Technology Officer

- Created GRC program to fast-track NIST 800-171/NIST 800-53 security control compliance
- Consulted with multiple airports to design security program for NIST CSF compliance with mapping to ISO/IEC 27001
- Created gap analyses for commercial clients seeking FAR and DFARS corporate security compliance
- Instrumental in expanding company into a local technology and security powerhouse; growth from 11 employees to 144; \$4M annual revenue to \$37M
- Created Commercial Division: VAR product portfolio, MSSP service creation, penetration testing/red team/ethical hacking, vulnerability assessments, IR/forensics, risk management, secure architecture/SSDLC program, outsourced CISO. Managed 5 penetration testing teams: Network, Web Application, Wireless, Social Engineering, and Critical Infrastructure (powergrid, SCADA)
- As outsourced CISO, performed Incident Response, Insider Threat and APT detection, and Mitigation duties for commercial clients
- Designed and managed development of a cloud-based Cyber Range used for both commercial and military offensive and defensive training, security capabilities vetting, and cybersecurity product testing
- Instructor for UCSD Rady Business School, training CEO/CIOs by translating security concepts and current issues into business-relevant solutions.
- Assisted Navy programs through cloud cybersecurity and acquisition wickets to transition from traditional to cloud infrastructure
- Won ~\$450M in contracts including Computer Network Attack and Defense, security engineering, SOA engineering services, and risk assessments of all U.S. Navy networks, systems, and applications
- Provided software, compliance, and security engineering services including threat modeling and remediation for classified Navy/Army

- Chemical/Biological/Radiological/Nuclear system and classified Navy/Coast Guard intelligence system
- Managed two teams of 30 security engineers providing cybersecurity GRC and engineering services to the Navy Certifying Authority through DIACAP and RMF. Security SME for cloud computing, SOA, virtualization, and cryptography. Authored Navy-wide cybersecurity governance
- Authored corporate security policies, corporate risk management, security plan, incident response plan, and DR/BCP
- Created security/IT lab for IT patch testing, security training, and prototyping
- Lead building of dynamic security awareness smartphone application for the DHS
- Lead building of prototypes for next-generation military Command and Control systems and cross-platform mobile applications
- Conducted international business development (Europe, Africa, Southeast Asia) for C4I engineering products and services

### **Layered Intelligence Corporation**

Sep 2004 – Dec 2006

San Francisco, CA

**Chief Technology Officer** 

#### Project: Millivox.Net

Managed team developing e-Commerce and collaboration website for the sales and secure distribution of digital content

#### **Project: Data Driven Software Corporation (d2sc.com)**

Created technology revitalization plan, risk mitigation strategies, enterprise architecture standards, security policy, and engineering procedures

#### **Project: Layered Global Services**

- Developed and ran the division performing managed technology offshoring.
- Managed software engineering teams around the world including the U.S., the Ukraine, Mexico, Russia, England, and Argentina.

### **UFO Communications**

Nov 2000 - Aug 2004

San Francisco, CA

**VP of Software Engineering** 

- Designed the Operations Support System (OSS) that automated the business processes of the telecommunications enterprise
- Managed the software engineering team that delivered seven releases of the OSS over four years, all on-schedule and under budget
- Worked with corporate attorneys to patent OSS processes and algorithms
- Managed tech due diligence enabling sale to Cogent Communications

### Shippers Network

Nov 1999 - Sep 2000

Carlsbad, CA

**Chief Technology Officer** 

 Designed and managed the engineering team to build a secure B2B Transportation Exchange and Transport Management System

eHNC (now Fair Isaac Corporation/FICO)

Jun 1999 – Nov 1999

San Diego, CA

**Lead Software Engineer** 

• Architected enterprise data integration standard; designed and implemented custom security authentication protocol

Science Applications International Corporation / Global Integrity / Tenth Mountain Systems San Diego, CA Dec 1996 - Jun 1999

**Senior Staff Security Engineer** 

- Architected, built, and demonstrated the world's first and only anonymous, authenticated security vulnerability, incident, and risk clearinghouse for the U.S. financial services sector (in conjunction with the U.S. Department of the Treasury). This system, called the Financial Services Information Sharing and Analysis Center (FS-ISAC), recently won the award for Excellence in Information Security at the 2013 RSA Conference. www.fsisac.com
- Pioneered the first security vulnerability advisory system (REACT Reflector) used to notify customers of security vulnerabilities based upon hardware, software, and architecture profiles
- Designed and built a host- and network-based security surveillance system (spyware) which detected and audited usage of certain key media types and reported the activity to remote servers
- Core developer in the Secure Electronic Transactions (SET) e-commerce protocol compliance suite
- Performed security and system architecture reviews for global financial institutions including some of the largest banks and trading floors in the U.S.

O'Reilly and Associates Sebastopol, CA Apr 1996 – Dec 1996 Software Developer, WebSite Development Team

• Maintained security and website production products

Science Applications International Corporation

Jul 1995 – Jun 1996

San Diego, CA

Consulting Software Engineer, PacMedNet Project

 Pioneered a \$38M global Electronic Health Record system that allowed medical treatment facilities to locate and securely exchange digital medical records and images world-wide

**Integrated Computer Management Solutions** 

Feb 1995 - Jul 1995

Dallas, TX

**Principal / Consultant** 

- Authored medical informatics software for a national hospital group
- Created an expert system for a telecommunications company

Science Applications International Corporation

Feb 1988 - Feb 1995

San Diego, CA

- System architect for one of the world's largest medical informatics systems;
   \$1.6 billion DoD healthcare project for Military Treatment Facilities worldwide
- Held various engineering and management positions throughout my tenure

**Digital Equipment Corporation**San Diego, CA

Jul 1985 – Feb 1988 Consulting Systems Manager, Software Group

**Bit-7 Computer Systems**San Diego, CA

Aug 1982 – Jul 1985 Contract Programmer

### **Training and Certifications**

- Certified PCI DSS Qualified Security Assessor (for PCI DSS compliance)
- Certified Information Systems Security Professional (CISSP), (ISC)2 License 372792
- Certificate of Cloud Security Knowledge (CCSK), CSA, Code 400627370396
- Negotiation and Leadership, Program on Negotiation (PON), Harvard Law School. November 2016
- Amazon AWS Solution Architect training, 2013
- RSA and Cloud Security Alliance Conference 2012, 2013, 2014, 2015
- BlackHat and DEFCON 2011, 2012, 2013, 2014, 2015, 2016, 2017, 2018
- BlackHat Incident Response (Mandiant) training
- BlackHat Advanced WiFi Penetration Testing training
- BlackHat Maltego (Social Engineering, Open Source Intelligence) training
- BlackHat Exploit Laboratory training (Vulnerability exploit creation)
- BlackHat Samurai Web Testing Framework training (web app pentesting)
- "Attacking, Defending, and Building SCADA Systems" training, BlackHat 2014
- "Assessing and Exploiting Industrial Control Systems with SamuraiSTFU" training, BlackHat 2013
- Financing Strategy: Sources of Capital and Business Plans, UCSD, March, 2015
- Agile Scrum Training, CollabNet
- Department of Defense Architecture Framework (DODAF) training
- VMWare vSphere/vCenter training
- Sitecore Certified Developer (.NET-based Content Management System; ASP.NET/C# and XSLT)

### **Speaking Engagements, Publications, Memberships**

- Author (USD, 4-hour course) Anatomy of a Hack. April 2018
- Speaker (NDIA) Hacking Demonstration, The tactics and views from the hacker's perspective. February 2017
- Speaker (FortneyScott) *The Cybersecurity Challenge: A Roadmap to Assessment and Compliance*. April 2017
- Author (Sentek), Social Engineering Defense Training. Oct 2016
- Panelist (NDIA Gold Coast) Small business cybersecurity; Defense contractor protection of DoD CUI data. August 2016
- Speaker (San Diego Business Services Alliance) *The Latest Cyber Threats from the Hacker Underground*. September 2015
- Speaker (Sentek, Barney&Barney, ESET) Preparing for the Inevitable: Best Practices to Protect Your Company from a Data Breach. June 2015.

- Speaker (San Diego Women in Finance) Cybersecurity Impact to the Bottom Line, October 2014
- Author (San Diego Cyber Center of Excellence) WiFi Security Standard. April 2015
- Panelist (AFCEA C4ISR Conference) Information as Warfare. April 2013
- Author (Defense Systems Magazine) *Military looking to DISA for clear direction on security in the cloud*. September 2012
- Speaker (KNSD-TV Channel 7/39 broadcast) Sentek High Tech Defense Boosts Economy. April 2010
- Cited, Corporations should follow government's lead on attribution of cyber attacks. The Daily Transcript. February 2010.
- Author, *Don't forget who's behind a cyberattack*. Washington Technology. February 2010.
- Cited, Local Arena Plays Large Role in Protecting Against Enemy Cyber Attacks. San Diego Business Journal. February 2010.
- Cited, Cloud computing has uncertainties, is moving forward. The Daily Transcript. October 2009.
- Cited, Governance, guidance necessary in the cloud. San Diego Daily Transcript. October 2009.
- Co-author, *Defining AFRICOM's mission*. Signal Online (an AFCEA publication). December 2008.
- Author, *Bridging the SOA divide for deployed assets*. Defense Systems. September 2008.
- Author, Supporting the National Anti-terrorism Initiative in the Philippines. May 2008.
- 2008/2009/2010/2011/2012/2013 San Diego Business Journal's Technology Executive of the Year finalist
- 2011/2012/2015 San Diego Magazine's Top Tech Exec Awards finalist
- Member, San Diego CISO Round Table
- Member, Tech San Diego CTO Round Table

### **References and Education**

Available on request